Hey guys, Shandra said welcome to
concept and coding and today in this
spring security video we are going to
discuss the next authentication method
which is basic authentication. So till
now we have seen the form login
authentication method and which was a
stateful authentication method and this
one is stateless authentication method.
So stateless authentication means server
do not maintain the user authentication
state. No session is maintained by the
server.
Okay. So why it's called basic? As from
the name it is clear it is basic like
very very simple. In this client has to
pass the username and password with
every request with every request. If you
are accessing the resources 100 times
you have to pass the username and
password with each and every request.
Right? And we have to pass this in the
authorization header. So this is the
form in the authorization header. We
have to form pass like this. It goes
like this in your request header. So
first one is basic which tells yes it is
a basic authentication method we are
using. Then your username colon the
password which is base 64 encoded. So
remember that it is always in a encoded
form not encrypted form right. So if
anybody intercepts your
request they can easily decode your
username and password. That's why we
call it like always use it on
HTTPS. Never use it over HTTP basic
authentication. Never use it basic
authentication over
HTTP because uh in the header we pass
username and password and that is only
in encoded form not encrypted
form. So now we know very basic about
this authentication method. Let's go
step by step. Okay. So first thing first
we have to create a user and we have
already seen in the video number 34 like
how to create a username and a user and
password dynamic users we can create
right we can even create a user in DB or
in memory. We have already seen all
possible ways to create a user. Okay.
So I am using for testing purpose I am
creating one user and I have hardcoded
that username is user password is pass
and I have provided a role admin. Okay.
So I have so when I will start my server
one user will get created and by default
it will go into inmemory. It would be
stored in inmemory not in DB. So if you
have any doubt with this how user is
created, how username password is
stored, what is the industry standard, I
would say that uh please go through this
video, you will get to know
that. So first thing first we have to
create a user. Now if any time you are
hitting a request, let's say I am
hitting one get request. Okay, here if
you
see / API/ users in this there is
something called
authorization in that I have what is the
O type I have choose basic O when I
click on the basic O I get an option to
provide a username and password so I
have provided my username user and
password is pass okay this one now when
I hit it right in the header it goes
like this
basic base 64 of your username colon
password. So this is your base 64
encoded form of your username colon
password. It goes like this. Okay.
So your username and password goes into
the header authorization header. So this
is the authorization field inside an
header and this is how it goes. Okay. So
if you open the basic authentication
filter. Okay. Now when you hit it right
when you click on uh send when you click
on send the control will comes to the
basic authentication filter. There you
can check this the request try to fetch
from the header authorization header. It
will try to fetch and there it will
decode it. And once it decoded you can
see that this was your
header
and after decoding it you can see your
username colon password. It is easy very
easy to decode. If it is not encrypted
then you can know that if anybody got
your encoded form they can decode it. It
does nothing but a base 64 only. Okay.
So this is how generally it's sent in
the request and you have to pass it in
each and every request.
Okay. So one question comes to our mind
that hey Shange why we need to send the
username and password in authorization
header only why not I can't pass it in
request body or query par parameter or
any other way like why only
header so these are the three possible
reasons in my view. First thing is
standard we have to follow one standard.
Let's say if you don't follow any
standard one client can pass you into a
request body another client pass you in
query parameter another client pass you
in header so it would be very difficult
to deal with different clients okay so
there is an RFC 7617 HTTP
standardization there it mentioned that
all the credentials has to be passed in
header only and it is important for
universally accepted
standard across APIs and client so that
no matter what clients what APIs if you
have to pass the credential you have to
pass it into header so that's a standard
so that you can write frameworks on top
of it okay the second thing is
security there are many web servers
which log the request body and even the
query parameters okay and that is not
safe because they might be logging it
for debugging or analytics purpose
Because what if your username and
password got logged inside that right
and you know that sometime the logging
tools which we use in a company it's
belongs to a third party it's not yours
okay so this is a security breach but
generally headers are not logged we
never log headers right so it's reduces
the risk of
exposure okay so security is one another
big reason why header is chosen
that yes we can pass username and
password inside an header and the third
one is support for all HTTP request in
my view if you see that post and put yes
we have a request body and uh we can
pass it but what about the get generally
get do not have body so generally if we
have a header then it can support
whether the API is get put post whether
the API accept body query parameter or
not. So header would always be there. So
it to maintain a consistency also this
uh required. So this is my reason like
why I think
that authorization header is preferred
for the username and
password. Okay. If that is clear now
let's understand a little bit more about
basic authentication and its flow. So
before I start I would highly recommend
you to go through this form based
authentication. Why? Because if you
remember from this video form based
authentication there are two part at one
part where user provide a username
password and the session got
created and second is where user pass
the session in the request itself and
then where it is got authenticated. So
here in the basic authentication it's a
combination of both. So from first part
yes username and password we are
providing but we are not creating
session in the second like there is no
second call there is nothing like a
second request. So in the one itself
like one we have the username password
then we have like uh authenticate and do
authorization authorization part. So in
the second step session plus
authorization happen
right. So in the one part itself of the
basic authentication user pass the
username password but we don't create an
session and when in the same request we
do the authorization that's all rest of
the flow is same as form based. So go
through that then it would be like a
piece of cake to understand
this. So here let's say that you are
hitting an API/ API/ users and in the
request and header you are
passing username and password. Okay. So
one of the security filter chain get
invoked. Now what would happen? So when
we are using basic
authentication the first filter which
get invoked is basic authentication
filter. This is the filter which will
get invoke. What the first thing it will
do? I already told you it will decode
the authorization header. I have already
told you in the code also. So this is
the first thing it do. It decode it.
Okay. So it decode the authorization
header. Now we have here username and
password. Plain username password. Now
the step is same as the form.
It create and pass the authentication
object to authentication manager. This
authentication object currently hold
this username, this password, nothing
else. So it has this username, it has
this password, nothing else.
Authentication is currently false and no
more
information. Okay. After this
authentication manager will delegate the
request to DAO authentication manager uh
provider. Okay. What DAO will do? So we
have the password coming right. So first
it has to hash it. So it will call the
password encoder. It will call the
password encoder and hash the incoming
raw
password. And after that what it will do
is it will fetch the user detail based
on the username from the DB. We have
created uh user details right at the
time of application startup. User
password role. So there is already a
user created. So that need to be
fetched. So in the fifth point it will
fetch those detail from user detail
service whether from inmemory or DB.
Once we get it it will validate the
incoming username and password with the
same or stored username
password. Once matched properly it will
update the authentication object. So now
same like previously username password
yes authenticated is true roles updated
to admin. Okay and it will return back
to the basic authentication
filter. Okay. Now what it will do at
ninth step it will save this
authentication object which is coming
this into a security context and put the
security context inside a security
context holder. This holder it will put
inside this. So this holder is
accessible across till controller also.
Okay. So we can say that now the
complete life cycle of a request this
security context would now be available.
Okay. If in future you want to fetch
whether user is authenticated what it is
role you can easily do
that. Okay. So now in the basic
authentication filter itself we have
done everything. We have uh match the
username password with the stored one
and then put it into the security
context holder the authenticated object.
Now this is the second filter get
invoked is authorization filter. It is
also exactly the same as
uh what we have done in the form based
login. Okay. So it goes to the
authorization filter where it says that
okay user is authenticated but user has
the permission to access the resource or
not. So that only we validated
it. Okay. So what we need to implement
it the flow is very very simple. Okay.
After that one the control proceed
further to dispatch a sublet. If there
is interceptor then it will get invoked
otherwise controller. Right. Very very
simple. And each and every time request
is passed it follows the same thing
because for each and every request
username and password is coming. So what
we need to implement
it first thing is same thing we need
dependency uh security and if you want
to so this is not required so you
remember that in form based login we use
this because we wanted to store the
session into the DB now here is no
session at all so we don't need this
dependency so only security is required
second thing is in
application.properties properties if you
want to create username password
hardcoded then it is required otherwise
dynamically you already know that in the
previous video we have already discussed
how to create a dynamic but I'm creating
a hard-coded one so in I have created
one
user now see this one this is classes
required so from the previous form login
video you know that what is the default
authentication method for spring boot it
is form based login so we have to
override this security filter chain and
we tell that hey the authentication
which we have to follow is HTTP basic
not HTTP form. So we are now overriding
the default one. So we are telling to
spring boot that your default is HTTP
form which is form authentication but we
are following HTTP basic which is B
basic authentication that is first
thing. Second thing is this is
stateless. So I have specifically
mentioned that session creation policy.
We already seen in the previous video
what is this. So this is
stateless in form based it is if
required if session is required create
it. But basic authentication it is
stateless. Session is never created and
each and every time you have to pass the
username password. So it is I have
specifically mentioned it is stateless.
Third thing CSRF I need to disable it
because from the first attack with demo
video right uh before we started
security I already told you that CSRF is
required mainly where the session is
maintained. So for the stateless CSRF is
not even required. What is CSRF attack?
How to protect it? we have already seen
uh before we started the spring uh
security videos right so you can also
follow that one so why I have disabled
it because this is a stateless and CSRF
is not a valid for the stateless uh
authentication it is only valid for
where session is maintained stateful
okay and here if you see that I have put
request matcher any API which matches
like
is should have a role like user. So I am
doing like an authorization filter here.
The similarly like what we did in the
previous video. So what would happen is
when the authentication happen the
request will go there it will check user
is trying to access an API API/ users.
Okay this is the API user is trying to
hit. So this API is required any role?
Yes. User role required. So user role
this is required. But what is the role
user has? User has role admin. So it is
not matching. So it will throw forbidden
error. Forbidden. So if match is let's
say user and here also it is user then
it will pass it and let it go. Okay. So
I have here just to show that for this
API I need a role user.
Okay. And that's all that's all you
needed it to implement the basic
authentication. Everything is handled by
framework. All we have to tell is like
which we have to override this spring
security filter chain and just tell
spring boot what we want.
Okay, very simple, right? But why it is
not used? Why what are the disadvantages
of basic authentication? Now you can say
that hey this is uh stateless, right? It
is good. But what what are the
disadvantages? Why it is not
popular? So see these are the three main
reason which I think it is not very
popular is one thing credentials are
sent in every
request right so that is one of the
biggest thing is like if HTTP is not
enforced then it can be intercepted and
decoded it we have already shown you
right it's encoded not encrypted. So one
is security reasons right and once the
credentials are compromised there is no
way you can do it only you have to
change the credentials that's the only
thing right there is nothing like a
session you invalidate the session or
token you invalidate the token nothing
you have to change the password nothing
else another thing is like it is not
very feasible that like uh user
experience is bad like for each and
every request you have to validate
authenticate yourself like username
password again and again and this makes
it not suitable for large scale
application. Why? Because it is an extra
overhead for first thing is your request
size increases even though with some
bytes but it will because of you have to
pass the authorization header your
username your password then you have to
encode it and then you have to add it to
your request. So some bytes will get
added to your already uh the request. So
it will increase the request size and
extra work like first it has to decode
then hashing of the incoming password
then fetch username and password from DB
existing one and then comparing it. So
all this thing has to be done again and
again and again. Okay. If your
application is accepting 1 billion
requests per day. So 1 billion times it
has to be
done. Okay. And the followup is DB
lookup. So now you are passing username
password. So for this username we have
to fetch it from the DB also like what
is the username and password is stored.
Then only we do compare right. So DB
lookup is also has to be done which
increase the latency also. So that's
because of all this issues.
this is not very
popular. Okay. So even though it it is a
stateless it's not popular and that's
where comes JWT into the
picture. Okay. And that's what we will
do
next. Okay guys so any doubt please feel
free to comment. We can discuss further
but this one is the very basic one. If
you already seen the form one then most
of the flow is very simple. So it's uh
self-escripted like the description
itself from diagram itself it will get
clear to you but still if there is any
doubt we can discuss further. Thank you.
Bye.